hey bre and ter here quick video on the
rkc plank this was about a year and a
half back I was talking to my friend Joe
sansalone and we were showing each other
how we do planks and I suppose that he
learned this from pav um who who helped
form the rkc and really popularized
kettle bells in America and pao's a
really Innovative guy he has a lot of
methods to make exercises more effective
anyway the way I was in plates was not
very effective and the way Joe showed me
was amazing I instantly felt it way more
in my abdominals but more importantly I
was using my glutes now here's why I
love the rkc plank so much when people
do a deadlift they come to the top you
you you want them finishing strong now
from the side view you'll see some hyper
extension you want that hyper extension
coming from the hips not the low back so
if you have weak glutes you'll see
people do this but if you have strong
glutes they're like this and it's all
hip hyperextension I'm not
hyperextending my lumbar spine this is
all coming from the glutes so if you
want people to be able to hold this
position right
here you know and they can't even do it
from a plank position how could they do
it from a deadlift so in my opinion this
exercise is an amazing exercise for
teaching how people how to hold that
poster your pelvic tilt that's one of
the roles of the glutes that no one
likes to talk about people say the
glutes are hip extensor hip abductors
hip external rotators they're also P Ste
pelvic tilters so here's what Joe had me
do um you know I was just blanking like
this and he said oh no no no that's not
good all right I want you to bring your
elbows out a little more and narrow the
base so that already makes it harder
because you're making it a longer lever
and then you're narrowing your base of
support so that alone makes it harder
then he said contract your quads to
straighten your legs out
and then I want you to squeeze your
glutes as hard as you can to where
you're posterior pelvic tilting of the
pelvis and what's interesting is to hold
that posterior pelvic tilt you know this
is the posterior pelvic tilt right here
just like that and it's just this subtle
rotation in the pelvis and uh to hold
that um now you're not you know you've
got to use the abdominals to hold that
as well so I measured the EMG activity
of this and I got like over twice as
much rectus abdominis and oblique
activity so you're going to feel this
way more in the ABS but also like I said
in the glutes and I think people need to
be able to rotate the pelvis and
dissociate the pelvis from the spine in
order to you know spare their low backs
and not have low back pain and to
transfer forces properly because the
gluteus maximus attaches to the sacr
tuous ligament it helps it's called a
force closure it helps transfer forces
through the the the Cilia uh joint close
it up seal it tight and uh and help you
transfer diagonal forces so here's how
you do
it remember I'm going to not set up here
I'm going to set a little further and
narrow my base okay from here I'm
looking down I contract the
quads okay and then from here squeeze
the glutes and I just hold it here
now what you'll find is weak people you
will see their
glutes some people can't even turn them
on from that position but some people
you'll see them and you'll kind of see
them fatiguing throughout the set you
should be able to hold that strong for a
whole minute and just when you squeeze
your glutes you should feel like you can
crack or wut I mean people have very
weak glutes it's pathetic you need
strong glutes and you need glute
endurance so when you're doing this
arcade see Plank turn those glutes on
maximally hold them in that position
again you should be able to do it for a
whole minute give it a try let me know
what you think